<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The snare broken, or, The natural and eternal deity of the Son of God, as also of the Holy Ghost, asserted by a person, who having been formerly a a [sic] Socinian, and then an Arrian, came at length, by a free consideration of the Scriptures, to be fully convinc'd of the truth of the Catholick faith concerning the blessed Trinity.</title>
            <author>Mayne, Zachary, 1631-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12605268</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12605268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 325:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The snare broken, or, The natural and eternal deity of the Son of God, as also of the Holy Ghost, asserted by a person, who having been formerly a a [sic] Socinian, and then an Arrian, came at length, by a free consideration of the Scriptures, to be fully convinc'd of the truth of the Catholick faith concerning the blessed Trinity.</title>
                  <author>Mayne, Zachary, 1631-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Z.M. A.M.</note>
                  <note>Written by Z. Mayne. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE SNARE BROKEN, OR, THE</hi> NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAL <hi>and</hi> ETERNAL <hi>DEITY of the SON of GOD; As alſo Of the HOLY GHOST, ASSERTED:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Perſon, who having been formerly a a <hi>SOCINIAN,</hi> and then an <hi>ARRIAN,</hi> came at length, by a free Conſideration of the <hi>SCRIPTURES,</hi> to be fully convinc'd of the Truth of the Catholick Faith concerning the Bleſſed TRINITY.</p>
            <q>Nihil tam Certum, quam quod ex Dubio Certum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year 1692.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64251:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THis Treatiſe was written by the Author (yet liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) about ten or twelve Years ſince, and thus occaſion'd to be publiſhed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> being ſuſpected (for ſome former carriages) to be a <hi>Socinian,</hi> was queſtioned by ſeveral as being ſuch: And a Friend of his intimating ſo much to him, he told his Friend, That he could ſufficiently diſprove that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny by a Paper that had lain by him theſe ten Years; which the ſame Friend deſir'd to ſee, and communicated to others for their Satisfaction: one of whom, that had been greatly prejudic'd againſt the <hi>Author,</hi> upon ſight of it, earneſtly deſir'd of him in a preſſing Letter that he would publiſh it for the common Good. To whom he reply'd, That if he would Print it, the <hi>Author</hi> would give him the Copy, with his Permiſſion to publiſh it, if he thought it might be of any Uſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_publisher">
            <pb facs="tcp:64251:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Publiſher</hi> of the following <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Truly congratulate that Event of Providence, which has brought to your hands ſuch a ſurprizing Vindication of the Truth in this Age of Infidelity and Apoſtacy. You are oblig'd not to let it ly any longer hid, and I think the Author is not to be excus'd by his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, for having ſuppreſs'd it ſo long. There is a Reſtitution we all owe to injur'd Truth; and I have alway eſteem'd it the greateſt Indication of a noble Mind, not to be <hi>afraid,</hi> or <hi>aſham'd</hi> to declare where I have trod amiſs; and to warn others from falling into thoſe pits, which I had much ado to eſcape. I am not a little ſenſible of ſome conſiderable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that have been given to the Adverſaries of the Holy Doctrine maintain'd in the following <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> by the <hi>Unwarineſs</hi> or <hi>intemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of ſome of its Vindicators; who, tho' no ordinary Maſters of Senſe and Learning, have either by the impreſſion of Orthodox Education, or Heat of Temper, or perhaps ſomething elſe, been inſenſibly prevail'd on to ruſh into the Battel, before they have been fully acquainted with the ſtrength, or Meaſures of the adverſe Party. I ſhall always deſpair of ſeeing any conſiderable Conquests made by the depth of <hi>Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Speculations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (be they in themſelves never ſo true,) or the toil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom labour of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> (be it never ſo incorrupted and impartial:) And I believe, hardly any one will expect much good from either of theſe ways, if he but conſiders the Humours of that Sect of Men we have to deal with, what <hi>Volzogen</hi> has written againſt the one, and <hi>Sandius</hi> perform'd in the other; the ſmall number of thoſe whoſe <hi>Heads are caſt into ſuch a Mold,</hi> (as a Modern <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſician</hi> phraſes it,) as to be able clearly to comprehend the <hi>former;</hi> or who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long enough to be ſufficient Judges of the <hi>latter:</hi> and the frequent inſucceſsfulneſs of ſuch Attempts that have been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in both theſe ways, with ſuch an ingenuity, ſolidity, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, as is not eaſily to be found. I do not at all doubt but that among the <hi>Anti-trinitarians,</hi> as well <hi>Arrians</hi> as <hi>Socinians,</hi> there are ſeveral who with great ſincerity ſeek after the Truth: Neither do I at all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that here are ſuch, who from the prevalency of <hi>Temper</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> are ſo far carried away by the <hi>Niceties</hi> of ſome <hi>Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical</hi> Divines, and the <hi>Uncertain</hi> Relations of ſome <hi>Church Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> as to throw away what they moſt earneſtly ſearch after. It will be no eaſy taſk to remove theſe Obſtacles, by which (as I am willing to judge) ſome well-meaning Perſons are perverted from the poſſeſſion of the greateſt and moſt noble Truths; but I truſt it will be no very hard one to engage ſuch to follow their own Methods, and leiſurely to examine the Steps which the worthy Author, (once under the ſame <hi>Infidelity,</hi> or <hi>Scruples</hi> with <hi>them,</hi>) has taken to find out the True <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, and to free himſelf from the <hi>Snare</hi> into which he was fall'n.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64251:3"/>
            <head>Erudito, ac Pio Lectori S.</head>
            <p>TE Oro, &amp; Obteſtor, Frater Chariſſime, per JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> Noſtri Viſcera, ut <hi>Chriſtianiſmi</hi> Profeſſionem per tot hominum <hi>Satanicorum</hi> dicta, Facta<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> 
               <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſſima</hi> vacillantem ſuſtentare totis Viribus annitaris. Veritatis Salutiferae ex oculis noſtris auferendae ingruentibus undi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Periculis Mecum ſemper Ingemiſcas. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t uſque Illi adhaerere poſſimus, qui dicit, <hi>Ego ſum Via, Veritas, ac Vita,</hi> Audiamus Illum etiam dicentem: <hi>Attollite Jugum meum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vos, &amp; Diſcite a Me, quia Mitis ſum, &amp; Humilis Corde.</hi> Ardentiſſimas Cogitationes Animum meum ingenti pondere quodammodo opprimentes juvat hoc <hi>Diſticho</hi> aliquatenus Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicare:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sola poteſt Submiſſa DEUM Mens Cernere CHRISTUM,</l>
               <l>Odit Mens HUMILEM quaeque SUPERBA DEUM.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Opto te bene Valere, atque Erudito hujus Tractatus Authori, Dulciſſimam tibi Veritatem propinanti, maximas habere Gratias.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64251:3"/>
            <head>The Natural and Eternal Deity of the <hi>SON</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> as alſo of the <hi>HOLY GHOST,</hi> Aſſerted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN, and therefore Courteous <hi>Reader,</hi> I hold my ſelf oblig'd in Conſcience to make what amends God ſhall enable me to the Publick for the wrong that I have done, but eſpecially to endeavour to repair the Glory of God my Saviour, and God the Holy Ghoſt, as I ſhall be enabled; which I fear I have by my ignorance, and Raſhneſs diminiſht, and for which I humbly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the pardon, and mercy of the Almighty. I was formerly of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Perſwaſion, and declar'd my ſelf ſo for about two moneths near the Year 1651, by which I know I griev'd many good Perſons that knew me, and had charitable thoughts of me, and I doubt I might make ſome to queſtion the truth, which they had believ'd; tho' I hope not many: for that I was neither buſy in meddling with the Conſciences of others, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was I of ability to manage an Argument with any great ſubtilty. But after about two moneths that I had convers'd with the <hi>Socinians</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Biddle,</hi> being then alive, obſerving many odd Notions that he had, as particularly that of the <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> I returned to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and converſed, and communicated with the Orthodox ever after. Yet I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I continued to doubt of thoſe matters, and was on and off in my thoughts about them for near twenty Years together. Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> who was then Preſident of our Colledge, was ſatisfied that I ſhould receive the Sacrament with him, tho' he knew my Doubts; becauſe, as he obſerved (and it was true) that I could never forego the Notion of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Death as a proper Sacrifice, whatever the <hi>Socinians</hi> offer'd to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in their Gloſſes, upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And I can, and do call God to witneſs, that what I write is not for worldly Intereſt. Nay, I am ſenſible that I may do my ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable damage by it: But I think it a piece of Honeſty at this time, to caſt in my Mite to the Treaſury of thoſe many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64251:4"/>worthy Labours, which will be occaſioned (as I ſuppoſe) to be publiſhed through the raw and bold Attempts of divers, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt our Saviour of his Natural Deity, as being the Eternal Son of God; and the Holy Ghoſt of his being the moſt High God alſo. — I am much troubled to think what Work Men may make of it upon this Subject. Learning, I ſuppoſe, was never ſo common, nor perhaps the Wits of Men of any Age ever more quick and ſmart, or the Humours of Men in a greater ferment, than they are now all over <hi>Europe:</hi> and now for the Philoſopher to fall to work with his Arguments, and the Linguiſt with his Criticiſms in a ſubject of the higheſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and indeed utterly ſurpaſſing the Wit of Man to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, might do a world of miſchief, and for all I can foreſee, ſet all <hi>Europe</hi> in another Flame, tho' that which the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Turk</hi> have kindled, ſhould be never ſo happily quenched. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I humbly adviſe (who am wholly diſintereſted further than as I am a Chriſtian, and have thought of the Subject now theſe 35 Years, and that with ſerious concern) Firſt; That Men would lay aſide their Philoſophy in inquiring into, and handly this ſubject; that is, as to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or intrinſick Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for it is impoſſible by reaſon to comprehend the Being of God. Secondly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That they wholly betake themſelves to a Scriptural conſideration of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and my thoughts what they are as informed by Scripture, after ſo long a Pauſe, as with ſhame I have mentioned, I humbly offer as followeth: only here obſerve that I deſign not to be ſo prolix, as to mention all, or the moſt Arguments that may be brought for the proof of the Deity of our LORD, or the Holy Ghoſt, but only thoſe that have chiefly ſway'd with me.</p>
            <p>And firſt, For that of our Saviour I conſider the clearneſs of his <hi>Praeexiſtence</hi> to his being Born of the Virgin. <q>Before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was, I am. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.58. Thou art not fifty years old (ſay the <hi>Jews</hi>) and haſt thou ſeen <hi>Abraham?</hi>
               </q> In the Verſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before; upon which our Saviour utters this, which certainly the <hi>Jews</hi> took in that ſenſe, as aſſerting a <hi>Praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence</hi> and thereupon took up ſtones to ſtone him. But it is more plainly aſſerted in <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. <q>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God. Ver. 14. And the Word was made Fleſh.</q> What was that which was made Fleſh, or became Fleſh, (for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but ſomething that was, before it was made or became Fleſh? Therefore the Word was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64251:4"/>before it became Fleſh. But in the ſecond Chap. of the <hi>Hebr.</hi> V. 13, 14. it is, yet much more plainly expreſſed: <q>And again, I and the Children that thou haſt given me;</q> ſpeaking of Chriſt, Ver. 14. <q>And becauſe the Children are partakers of Fleſh and Blood, he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the fame, that through Death he might deſtroy him that had the power of Death, that is the Devil.</q> He in like manner <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, took part with the Children, whom he was to Redeem by dying in fleſh and blood. Who took part, but he that had another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before? He took part upon deſign in order to an end, <hi>viz.</hi> That of dying, therefore he was a deſigning Perſon before, a Perſon of Counſel, and Wiſdom, and great deſigns. Another great Argument to me of his <hi>Praeexiſtence,</hi> which hath often affected me, is his being with the Father, hearing from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Doctrine that he afterwards preached: Coming from the Father, which our Saviour ſo often makes mention of, as being before his coming into the World. Now for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that is made by the <hi>Socinians,</hi> that our Saviour was caught up into Heaven ſometime before his Appearing in the World, in the Courſe of his Miniſtry, and converſed with God, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did in the Mount; it is a <hi>Non ſcriptum,</hi> and to me looks like a very unſavoury Fiction. How roundly, and fully doth our Saviour expreſs this thing? <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.28. <q>I came forth from the Father, and am come into the World, again I leave the World, and go to the Father.</q> That is; After my Death, I leave off being here in the World, and go to Heaven to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther altogether; as before I was Born of my Mother, and came into the World, I was with my Father altogether, rejoycing always before him: And upon this as fully, and roundly ſpoken the Diſciples Anſwer. <q>Now ſpakeſt thou plainly, and ſpakeſt no Proverb:</q> Now we know and believe that thou cameſt forth from God; that is from God as his Manſion place, where he had ever been before he came to them. So <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.62. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour having before aſſerted that he was the Bread of Life, which came down from Heaven; and finding that this with other Myſterious expreſſions, had offended, many of his Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, he asks them in Ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <q>What, ſaith he, doth this offend you? What, and if you ſhould ſee the Son of Man aſcend up where he was before?</q> Is it not as credible that I ſhould come down from Heaven, the place of my Reſidence at firſt; as that I ſhould aſcend thither at laſt; and that viſibly ſo, as ye ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64251:5"/>ſee it with your eyes? Doth not this ſpeak plainly that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not only with the Father occaſionally, and for a time of Inſtruction only, (as the <hi>Socinians</hi> would have it) but that he was in Heaven, as his Manſion, and Dwelling-place for ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and here upon Earth only occaſionally, and for a time? Give me Scriptures in their plain, and obvious ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without a force, or a ſtrain: for if once Men begin to ſtrain for the ſenſe, farewell the genuine Truth; and therefore I do, and have often deſpair'd of Truth, when it is once engag'd in Diſpute; when Men for their Credit will ſtrain their Wits: and therefore no wonder if they ſtrain the Word, and wreſt it from its genuine ſenſe and ſcope.</p>
            <p>And indeed while I was a <hi>Socinian,</hi> (for I will do all Men and Parties (that I have to do with) all the right I can) for I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pretend to an Univerſal Candor;) I ſay while I was a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian,</hi> I was ſo <hi>ex animo;</hi> and then went to take Scriptures in their plain ſenſe, ſcope and tendency, and did never think it adviſeable to undertake to be a Patron of that Cauſe, for that I ſaw Diſputes would be endleſs, and Diſputants might hold an Argument <hi>pro, &amp; con</hi> in this Subject to the end of the World, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral Diſtinctions that have been framed. But now I believe, That taking Scriptures according to plain ſenſe and meaning, for our Saviours Natural Deity, hath the better of my ſo taking them when I was a <hi>Socinian;</hi> and the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Belief I ſubmit to the Reader of my Arguments.</p>
            <p>So much, I humbly conceive, may ſerve to be ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Praeexiſtence</hi> of our Saviour, to his being Born of the <hi>Virgin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here comes in the <hi>Arrian:</hi> And, ſaith he, I grant our Saviour was <hi>Praeexiſtent</hi> to his being Born of the <hi>Virgin;</hi> and he was made Fleſh, who had exiſted Perſonally before, and he was made to partake of Fleſh and Blood, as thoſe that were to be his Children did, that he might die for them, and Redeem them. He had dwelt in Heaven before ever he came into the World; and was not only caught up into Heaven to ſee, and hear what he was to reveal; but he was only a Created Spirit, or Angel, and was in the fulneſs of time united to the Humane Nature, by the power of the Holy Ghoſt. This Opinion, I confeſs I have inclined to alſo: But I am alſo beaten out of this by the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe, or whoſoever was the Author of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in the firſt and ſecond Chapters, Ch. 1.13.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64251:5"/>
               <q>To which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, Sit thou at my Right Hand, until I make thine enemies thy foot-ſtool?</q> 
               <q>Are they not all Miniſtring Spirits?</q> Ver. 5. <q>Unto which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee?</q> Ver. 6. <q>And again when he bringeth his Firſt Begotten into the World, he ſaith, And let all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God worſhip him.</q> Now if all the Angels of God muſt worſhip him, and that God the Father ſaid not ſo, or ſo to any one of all the Angels; he is clearly ſet forth as one above all the Orders of Angels; and therefore in plain meaning above all Creatures; therefore no leſs than God. Nay, whereas the Apoſtle only words it, Worſhip him all ye Angels; or, Let all the Angels of God worſhip him, it is in the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi> whence the Apoſtle quotes the Expreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. 'Worſhip him 'all ye Gods. So that whatever Titular God there is, or can be conceived in the whole Creation, they are all inferiour to him, and he is not of their Rank, or Kind; therefore not a Creature, as to his Divine Nature, but of the proper genuine Eſſence of the moſt High God; as a Son is of the fame kind with his Father; and we know there is but One God in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, tho' the Son, and the Father among us make Two in number.</p>
            <p>But that which yet further, and beyond all theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth me that our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> is God by Nature, is, That he undertook to Anſwer, and Satisfy the Law for Sinners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'The ſting of Death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law.</hi> It were a very ſmall matter for us to Die, were it not for Sin that follows us to our Graves, to Judgment, and to Hell; and Sin could have no ſtrength in it to Damn us, and caſt us into Hell, were it not for the Law of God that forbids it, and threatens Death, and Hell upon the Commiſſion of it. Now this Law of God is impowred and invigorated with all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Authority of that God that made it, and binds down the Sinner unavoidably to deſtruction, until ſome one come that can deal with this Law ſo full of Majeſty, and Authority: Until, I ſay, ſuch a One come and free us from this Law, the Sinner cannot be ſet at Liberty from the Condemning Power of it. I meddle not with that Queſtion, Whether God can Pardon without a Satisfaction, or no; I think it is evidently declar'd that he will not, <hi>Without ſhedding of Blood there is no Remiſſion; Heb.</hi> 9.22. and therefore it comes all to one in this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64251:6"/>matter. Now what Creature tho' never ſo Great, Wiſe, and Innocent, dares appear in the face of the Law to reſcue the Priſoners; for all the World is become guilty before God, <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> There is no Creature but is ſubject to the Law of God; and the utmoſt Good that the Creature can receive from the Law, is to be acquitted in his own Perſon, having never offended it. Why yet here comes a Champion into the field our Lord JESUS by Name; and he comes into the field as it were (for that ſeems to be the Apoſtle's Scheme, Habit, or Form of Expreſſion) and demands Liberty for the Law's Captives, which he hath Liberty from the Father to Redeem; not by offering Violence to the Law, but by paying a Price which ſhall be tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont to the Damnation, or Eternal Sufferings of all the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Men, and Women of all Ages of the World, and by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of God the Father the Law muſt yield, may not detain them any longer under the Sentence of Condemnation, in Caſe this Great Redeemer Pay to the Law a Valuable Conſideration, which accordingly he did by Dying. And whereas before we were all Naturally, or by Condition of our Natures as it were Married to the Law; the Law is now by the Death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> reputed as Legally-dead; and we are no Adultereſſes, tho' we be Married to another; that is, to the Son of God, who Redeem'd us, bought us off from the Law, and Marries us to Himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the New Conditions of Faith, and ſincere Obedience: and this ſhall now be accepted at our hands, as effectually, as perfect unerring Obedience would have been from our firſt Husband the Law, had we ſtood Innocent. I confeſs the <hi>Tropes</hi> ſeem to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere, thoſe of Champion; and Surety, thoſe of the Fields and the Court; but they are all juſtified by Expreſſions, that we may pick up out of the Apoſtle's Diſcourſes of this ſubject. And if our Underſtandings be at laſt well inform'd, it is no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what become of the <hi>Figures,</hi> which were only by the Fancy to introduce the matter into our Underſtanding. That <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Death-was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Price of our Redemption is expreſſed often; and that he delivered us from the Law is as often found; and that this Law was not only the Ceremonial, but the Moral Law, I think it as plain: For elſe how ſhould the whole World become guilty before God, but by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Moral Law, which is the <hi>Strength of ſin?</hi> And how could our Saviour deliver the <hi>Gentiles</hi> from their ſin, but by weakning its Strength; that is, taking off the Condemning
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64251:6"/>Power of the Law? And how could he take off the Condemning Power of the Law, but by ſuffering the Penalty of it? And what Creature could ſuſtain the Wrath of God, which the Law was armed with? Methinks it is as plain as one of the Firſt Principles in <hi>Metaphyſicks.</hi> Who but God could ſuſtain the Wrath of God, and not periſh under it? And yet this we find Performed by our Saviour, as it had been Prophecied of him, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. <q>Awake, O Sword, againſt my Shepherd, and againſt the Man that is my Fellow, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: Smite the Shepherd, and the Sheep ſhall be ſcattered.</q> This is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by our Saviour to himſelf, in the very Evening of his Paſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.31. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.27. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.32. And we ſee it accompliſhed in theſe words, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me?</hi> Now by this Suffering <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſatisfied the Law; and in that way did as it were Conquer it: He <note>PLACE="foot" n="*" I am apt to think that this Expreſſion of <hi>Nailing it to his Croſs,</hi> may be chiefly intended of the <hi>Ceremonial Law;</hi> becauſe that which was Nailed to the Croſs, was Cancelled; whereas that is not true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Moral Law;</hi> tho' it were left in a ſenſe Dead, that is as to the Power of Condemnation againſt Believers.</note>
               <hi>Nailed it to his Croſs, Col.</hi> 2.14. The Law brought <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> to his Death, and Croſs more effectually than the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romans;</hi> and there our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour left the Law for Dead; as it is expreſſed at large in an Elegant <hi>Allegory</hi> by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. the firſt 6. Verſes: <q>Know ye not, Brethren, for I ſpeak to them that know the Law, how that the Law hath dominion over a Man, as long as he liveth. For the Woman, which hath an Husband, is bound by the Law to her Husband ſo long as he liveth; but if the Husband be dead, ſhe is free from the Law of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. So then if while her Husband liveth ſhe be married to another Man, ſhe ſhall be called an Adultereſs; But if her Husband be dead, ſhe is free from that Law; ſo that ſhe is no Adultereſs tho' ſhe be married to another Man. Wherefore, my Brethren, ye alſo are become Dead to the Law by the Body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that ye ſhould be married to another, even to Him that is raiſed from the Dead, that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God. For when we were in the Fleſh, the motions of Sin, which were by the Law did work in our Members to bring forth fruit unto Death: But now we are delivered from the Law, that being dead wherein we were held (that is the Law) that we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64251:7"/>ſhould ſerve in newneſs of Spirit, and not in the oldneſs of the Letter.</q> Here you ſee the Law is Dead by the Body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Crucified, and thereby we are free to be married to another, even to Him that is raiſed from the Dead; nay, who raiſed himſelf from the Dead; For, ſaith he, <q>I have power to lay down my Life, and I have power to take it again, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.18.</q> Now; who can this be but God, but the Natural Son of God? For, who could confront the Law of God, without doing Affront unto it, and leave it for dead by dying, and yielding to it, and not periſh under it? Or, how could any other Nature give Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to his Suffering to make it a juſt Price of Redemption of the whole World, but the Natural Son of God?</p>
            <p>There are many other things and Expreſſions, which have greatly affected and moved me to my preſent perſwaſion; as that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12. His making and deſtroying the World: Our being commanded to Worſhip and Truſt in Him, as God, even as we Honour the Father: His Saying, I, and the Father are One: His Anſwering <hi>Philip</hi> as he did, when he deſir'd him that he would ſhew them the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.8. <q>
                  <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaith unto him, Have I been ſo long time with you, and yet haſt thou not known me, <hi>Philip?</hi> He that hath ſeen me; hath ſeen the Father:</q> Which fully accords with that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3. <q>God hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son, whom he hath appointed Heir of all things; by whom alſo he made the Worlds: who being the Brightneſs of his Glory, and the Expreſs Image of his Perſon.</q> — A Native, and as it were, a Domeſtical Expreſſion of one that is a Son by Nature. And then the Intimacies that our Saviour ſignifies that he had with his Father: <q>The Father loveth the Son, and ſheweth him all things that himſelf doth, and he will ſhew him greater things then theſe, that ye may marvel. For as the Father raiſeth up the Dead, and quickeneth them, even ſo the Son quickeneth whom he will, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20, 21.</q> 
               <q>The Son can do nothing of himſelf, but what he ſeeth the Father do; for whatſoever things he doth, theſe alſo doth the Son like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Ver. 19. As the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo hath he given to the Son to have Life in himſelf, Ver. 26.</q> Which Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion I take to be Incommunicable to any Creature. Theſe things may ſuffice to have been ſpoken as the Grounds of my Belief concerning the Natural Deity of God the Son; I come in the next place to give the Reaſons for my Belief, That the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64251:7"/>Holy Ghoſt is God of the fame Eſſence with the Father, and the Son, and not a meer Creature; yea a Perſon, and no meer Power: And in this I ſhall be very Brief, becauſe the Evidences are not ſo many, tho' they are as Effectual. — And here firſt, It is plain that the Spirit of God by its Omnipotent Incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation did produce all the Variety of Creatures, when it moved upon the face of the Waters, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. Again, All Chriſtians acknowledge that the Scriptures were written by Men Divinely Inſpir'd; they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Inſpir'd, or Spirited, and breath'd on by the Spirit of God: and who can ſanctifie the heart but he that knows the heart; and who knows the heart but God? The heart is deceitful above all things, and deſperately wicked; who can know it? 'I the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9, 10. <q>Why hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan filled thine heart to lye unto the Holy Ghoſt? thou haſt not ly'd unto Men, but unto God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3, 4.</q> All the Gifts given to the Church were given by the Spirit of God, and that with an <hi>Authentick</hi> Authority, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. <q>All theſe worketh that one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, dividing to every Man ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as He Will.</q> And to demonſtrate how the <hi>Spirit,</hi> as a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a Divine Spirit aſſumeth his Authority, as God; ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. <q>As they miniſtred to the Lord, and faſted, the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the Work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I have called them.</q> Can this be the Voice and Command of any True Spirit, inſeriour unto God? But to conclude; and to give in the laſt place the greateſt Inſtance that affects me: for that is my Deſign eſpecially to declare with what <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Mediums,</hi> I am chiefly induc'd to ſettle in the <hi>Orthodox Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</hi> It is that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <q>Howbeit we ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are Perfect, yet not the Wiſdom of this World, nor of the Princes of this World, that come to nought.</q> The Apoſtles had the Treaſury of a Celeſtial Philoſophy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, which they publiſhed, and diſcourſed, and made it their Buſineſs ſo to do. It was indeed a Myſterious Wiſdom, Ver. 7. <q>But we ſpeak the Wiſdom of God in a Myſtery, even the hidden Wiſdom, which God ordained before the World unto our Glory:</q> Ver. 8. <q>Which none of the Princes of this World knew:</q> Ver. 9. <q>But as it is written, Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither have enter'd into the Heart of Man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</q> Well, how came they to know this Recluſe hidden Myſterious Wiſdome, which the very Chief of the World, Princes, and Philoſophers did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64251:8"/>not know; neither had enter'd into the Heart of Man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive? Why, Ver. 10. <q>But God hath Revealed them to us by his Spirit:</q> Why, how did the Spirit know? Why, the <q>Spirit ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things, even the Deep things of God.</q> There are none of the Secrets of Eternity but the Spirit knows them inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately. How ſo? The Apoſtle hath not done with it yet, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth further, and proves by a notable ſimilitude, Ver. 11. that the Spirit muſt needs know all that God knows, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think muſt needs be God; the words are theſe: <q>For what Man, knoweth the things of a Man, ſave the Spirit of a Man that is in him? Even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man:</q> It is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and it is poorly tranſlated <hi>No Man,</hi> it ought to have been tranſlated (as I humbly conceive) <hi>No one, neither Man not Spirit, nor any Creature; No one but the Spirit of God.</hi> And if the Spirit of a Man be not Eſſentially One with a Man, what is there One with him? And now being but a Similitude, it cannot be preſſed to a Sameneſs; as <hi>Nullum ſimile eſt idem:</hi> Yet I muſt humbly conceive the <hi>ſimile</hi> could not have been made without Blaſphemy, had not the Spirit been of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence: For what Proportion can there be betwixt Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and Finite; ſo that the Spirit, or Holy Ghoſt ſhould be to God, as the Spirit of a Man is to him, to know all his ſecrets, to ſearch into them, and from his perfect intimate knowledge of all the ſecrets of God to be able to communicate them to us? The Spirit is ſo one with the Father and the Son, as that there is no Myſtery hidden, or that can be hidden from him: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is God with the Father and the Son: and as here it is ſpoken perhaps chiefly of his Intimacy with the Father, who ordinarily ſuſtains the name of God: So in <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.15, 16, 17. is mention made of his Intimacy with the Son: <q>He ſhall take of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</q> So here you ſee is the Counſel of the <hi>Trinity.</hi> No wonder therefore where there is ſo great an Intimacy and Oneneſs, if they often appear together; the Father in a Voice, and the Spirit in a Dove upon the Son: no wonder if theſe be the Three that are ſaid to bear Record in Heaven. If Baptiſm be ordained to be celebrated in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; and (to give the laſt ſweet and bleſſed Farewel to my proofs) if the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conclude his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. with this Valediction; <q>The Grace of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Love of God the Father, and the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt be with you all. Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64251:8"/>
I have now only this to add touching the Doctrine of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> That tho' I believe this Eſſential Unity, which I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, and I hope, prov'd, yet that I ſuppoſe there is a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to behad to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or difference of theſe Perſons in the <hi>Trinity.</hi> For, as I humbly conceive, they that are of the Orthodox Opinion, as touching the Unity of the Three Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, are in great danger of Non-attendance to this Real Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that there is between the ſeveral Perſons; and are ready to ſwallow up all the Difference and Diſtinction or Diſtinctneſs in the Unity, and to think the Difference to lye only in a various and different Manifeſtation of the Being of God. Whereas there are ſo plain different Attributes, or Attributions of the Three Perſons, as if they were Three diſtinct Beings. The Father is manifeſtly the <hi>Fons Trinitatis,</hi> the Fountain of the Trinity; The Son is united to our Nature ſo, as the Father is not, and the Spirit, is not: The Son died in our Nature; ſo did not the Father, nor the Spirit. The Son was ſent by the Father; ſo was not the Father by either the Son, or the Holy Ghoſt: The Holy Ghoſt was ſent by the Father in the Name of the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. and ſent by the Son himſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7. The Father is the Perſon on whom our, Faith and Hope do ultimately terminate, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. So it doth not on the Son, or Holy Ghoſt: The Father in the Work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption ſuſtains the Perſon of the Parties offended, and yet giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son in order to the Reconciling the World to himſelf the Son the Perſon of Mediator, the Spirit applies all that is done by the Father and the Son, in Conviction, Converſion, Quickning, Comforting, Sealing, and Interceſſion within us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. I could inſtance in many more Particulars, which ought to have a ſerious conſideration; eſpecially the great Buſineſs of Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now in Heaven, where the Son Miniſters as a Kingly Prieſt at his Father's Right hand, in the true Tabernacle, which God hath pitched, and not Man. Is there not a great diſtinction here made betwixt the Father and the Son in ſuſtaining two different Perſons? And (what is conſequent upon this Obſervation of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) methinks it ſhould ſeem highly Rational to every Chriſtian, every one that owns the Myſtery of the Trinity, That as there are Three diſtinct Perſons, that All juſtly claim the Name and Title of God as they have the Eſſence; ſo that they ſhould All (that is Each) have their diſtinct Honour from him according to the ſeveral Diſcoveries that are made of them, of their ſeveral diſtinct Habitudes, and Relations to us, and that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64251:9"/>it ſhould not ſeem ſo abſurd a Notion, as I find it doth to ſome, that we may have a diſtinct Communion with the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Trinity:</hi> For if it be nothing elſe but to endeavour to Abear our ſelves with diſtinct, Honourable Thoughts, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions towards them according to the ſeveral Attributions, or Parts Aſſign'd to them, and moſt really. Aſſum'd by them for our Good; and to do this with the greateſt Reverence, and Joy that we can conceive in our Minds, what is this leſs than to have Communion with the Three Perſons diſtinctly, yet not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively: to love the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in ſincerity, to believe in him, <q>Ye believe in God (that is in the Father) believe alſo in me; and by him we are to believe in God, that is the Father, that by him our Faith and Hope may be in God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</q> The words at large are theſe: <q>Who by him do believe in God that rais'd him up from the dead, and gave him Glory, that your Faith and Hope might be in God.</q> And as this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be endeavour'd and done by us, as one Part of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to wit, that on our Part, ſo we find Two of the Divine, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons promiſed to come to us together, in caſe we do the Will of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21, 23. <q>Jeſus anſwer'd and ſaid unto him. If a man love me, he will keep my words, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him, and make our abode with him.</q> And do you think the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt ſhall be deny'd to that Perſon, where the Father, and the Son come and dwell? And is not here Communion with the Three Perſons? and yet I deſire all this may be underſtood modeſtly and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And indeed, however it fare with the Notion of theſe things, the Things themſelves ſhall never be underſtood, and experienc'd, but by thoſe that are Humble indeed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Z.M.</hi> A.M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64251:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
